A Guide to the Benson John Lossing Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7857
Benson John Lossing Collection
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7857
25 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [1963 December 17] 1965 March 6
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "Lossing's Field Book of the Revolution," article by Benson John Lossing, [1852 September]; AMS, 7 p.
    [Published as a letter to the editor of
    The American Whig Review
    (Oct. 1852); critical of the article "Lossing's Field Book of the Revolution" (
    American Whig Review
    , Sept. 1852)]
  - " John Wakefield Francis" (obituary by Benson John Lossing), [1861]; AMS, 3 p.
  - " Henry Wadsworth Longfellow" (biography by Benson John Lossing), [Post 1882 March 24]; AMS, 6 p.
  - Short quotation about uttering truths, n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
- Letters
  - Benson John Lossing to John Wingate Thornton with printed circular attached, 1852 January 30; ALS, 4 p.
    [Explains why he has not returned the paroles which he is using in the appendix to the
    Pictorial Field Book of the Revolution
    . Refers to the attached circular which requests material for the
    Pictorial Field-Book of the War of 1812
    and a history of the French domain and advertises his
    . Outlines how he plans to approach the upcoming projects, including extensive travel to collect material. Mentions: Florida, Andrew Jackson, John Burgoyne, Quebec, Fond du Lac, French Jesuits and traders, New Orleans, Creek County. ]
  - Benson John Lossing to Elizabeth Oakes Smith, 1855 November 3; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks her for her rebuke of something published in the
    Daily Times
    of that day. Expresses shock at "The indecency of your assailant's words and innuendos." A handwritten note on the back page says, "Mr. Lossing here refers to an attack upon me by Anne Estelle ? Lewis. "]
  - Benson John Lossing to William A. Whitman, 1859 February 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Acknowledges receipt of and thanks for a photograph of Peale's ( ? Charles Willson Peale or James Peale) etching of George Washington in 1787. Says he would appreciate having the photograph of a map he offered to send. Adds that he would like anything of the "hoary" past which he can send him. Relates some quotations in describing himself.]
  - Benson John Lossing to James Lorimer Graham, Jr., 1859 October 15; ALS, 2 p.
    [Explains why he has not written sooner. Regrets that he cannot help him, though he is flattered by Graham's intention to illustrate Lossing's
    Pictorial Field Book of Revolution
    for presentation to the historical society. Explains that he has few autographs and no duplicates. Says the papers he has used were borrowed and that the papers Graham saw in his room were placed in the state archives in Albany. Mentions that the papers of Philip John Schuyler which he now has will probably be placed in "our Historical Society." Mentions:
    The Life and Times of Philip Schuyler
    . ]
  - Benson John Lossing to Edwin Denison Morgan, 1862 September 10; ALS, 2 p.
    [Asks for a promotion for William Henry? Adriance to lieutenant in the 24th (Oswego) regiment. Mentions his bravery in "the late 3 days' battles in Virginia. " Gives background of attempts by others to gain his promotion. Mentions: Dewitt Clinton Littlejohn, Col. Rotch (in other handwriting in upper left corner.)]
  - Justus Starr Redfield to Benson John Lossing, 1863 January 3; ALS, 10 p.
    [Mentions a letter from Lossing which didn't reach him. Expresses his regret at how little he has to show for 53 years of life. Mentions the loss of first his means of living and now his health (to "breakbone fever" [dengue]). Discusses the false belief that Italy's climate is beneficial to invalids. Mentions the prevalence of both intermittent fever and influenza. Describes in depth the houses and humidity. Speaks of his wife Elizabeth Eaton Jones Redfield's pulmonary problems. Says there is much to interest the traveller, but that a knowledge of the Italian language and history, as well as Greek history, is essential. Gives a brief history of Otraunto, including its sacking by the Turks in 1480. Mentions his own lack of knowledge of the area and his desire to write its history. Gives a colorful description of the olive trees. Speaks of the "imbecility" ruling in the United States and expresses his wish to have Thomas Jonathan (Stonewall) Jackson commanding the North instead of Abraham Lincoln, his Cabinet and "half of his biggest generals." Compares the Battle of Fredericksburg(12/13 and 12/14) to the Battle at Richmond and the Bull Run Campaign. Begs Lossing to stop overworking himself and says his histories will benefit from his traveling to Europe now and writing later. Expresses pleasure that Archie is doing well and sends his and his wife's regards to Archie and his family. Mentions: Early Christians, Helen Sweet Lossing, Archie's mother, William Charles Redfield, John Gadsby Chapman, Temple of Minerva, Tarauto (Italy), Naples (Italy), Mahometanism, Joseph Kenny Meadows' "Falstaff."]
  - Benson John Lossing to C. McAllister, 1865 July 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Mentions his failure to acknowledge McAllister's letter with an offer of assistance. Thanks him for the photo of Bishop Potter ( ? Alonzo Potter or Horatio Potter). Says he's busy readying volume 1 of his
    Pictorial History (later Field Book) of the Civil War in the United States of America
    , (probably) for the press. Mentions that Lewis "Lew" Wallace and his wife Susan Arnold Wallace are their guests and that he spent the day before with Gen. Crawford (probably Samuel Wylie Crawford). Expresses hope for restoration of Mrs. McAllister's health and says a visit at Benson John Lossing's in the fall should be the finishing touch. Mentions: Fanny.]
  - Benson John Lossing to Charles Chauncey Burr, 1866 September 12; AL, 1 p.
    [Says Harper and Brothers are about to put his
    Pictorial Field Book of the War of 1812
    in type. Mentions an included sketch of the history of the two political parties of that time. Asks where he can find a copy of a 7-29-1792 letter from George Washington to Alexander Hamilton regarding Hamilton's uttering of "Shameless political sentiment. Mentions:
    A Youth's History of the Great Civil War in the United States from 1861 to 1865
    by Rushmore G. Horton. ]
  - Benson John Lossing to Col. Frank M. Etting, 1867 November 11; ALS, 3 p.
    [Answers a June 1866 letter which had arrived while he was in the South and had just surfaced. Says he wrote to Brantz Mayer for Etting's address. Encloses some photographs and returns the autographs of Count Rumford (pseudonym of Benjamin Thompson). Speaks of his procrastination in making a drawing of the seal, but says he has now done both it and the signature. Asks if he has the motto on the ribbon, tells how he reads it and questions the repeat of the word "lege." Mentions Edward Young. ]
  - Benson John Lossing to Harvey Gridley Eastman, 1870 July 4; ALS, 4 p.
    [Regrets that he can't take part in the dedication of a memorial fountain honoring the soldiers of Duchess County. Describes a "soldier's monument" in Honesdale, PA, and expresses a desire for a similar one in Poughkeepsie near the fountain. Calls the objections of others to such a monument un-American. Mentions a sketch of the Honesdale one, which he promised to send to General smith but has mislaid. Mentions: Romans.]
  - Benson John Lossing to Samuel Ward Francis, 1871 December 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks Francis for the copy of the
    Newport Daily News
    containing the notice of the death of Henry Theodore Tuckerman. Says Evert Augustus Duyckinck has just recommended that he ask Tuckermant to write a notice of Joseph Green Cogswell for Lossing's new magazine (probably
    American Historical Record and Repertory of Notes and Queries
    ), a prospectus of which is enclosed. Says he has prepared an obituary of Tuckerman. Says the evening paper reports the death of Sidney Edwards Morris. ]
  - Benson John Lossing to Charles Colcock Jones, 1873 January 11; ALS, 1 p.
    [Mentions seeing the prints of ? "Diez" at Mr. Pierson's, the engraver. Says he told Pierson to send Jones 36 copies without charge and wonders if Jones received them.]
  - Benson John Lossing to Lewis Jacob Cist, 1874 June 1; ALS, 3 p.
    [Thanks for the letter and enclosures. Regrets not receiving the
    Cincinnati Commerical
    with its notice of Cist's collection in time to put a notice in the June issue. Says he received the catalogue a few days ago. Says apparently the notice didn't reach the publishers in time. Explains the publishing schedule of the
    . Sympathizes with Cist's push with engagements and expresses appreciation of Cist's sending autographs. Discusses Vassar College, of which he has been trustee and cooperator. Says he will send a catalogue for this term.]
  - Benson John Lossing to William Leete Stone, 1875 February 16; ALS, 1 p.
    [Regrets that he can't subscribe to Stone's book due to financial problems. Mentions hard times affecting book sales and paying for stock for the farm.]
  - Benson John Lossing to Helen Sweet Lossing, 1882 September 28; ALS, 4 p.
    [Writes from a church convention describing his schedule and mentioning several conferences. Says Morgan Dix is seeking someone to write a history of Trinity Church. Says he is watching the papers for news of a certain ship being in port and will go on board to see Edwin if it is. Wishes Miriam and Alice could go on board with him and lays out a plan for their possible visit. Speaks briefly of his accommodations. Mentions: Mr. Weills, wife and daughter; Henry L. Ziegenfuss; Stephen H. Synnot; Robert Fulton Crary; Le Grand Dodge; Mr. Sandford; William A. Davies; Sheldon Davis; Philander Kinney Cady; Horatio Potter; Mrs. Van Riper; "Pet"; Mr. Segelken.]
  - Benson John Lossing to Tristram Coffin, 1888 June 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks Coffin for his letters and his interest in Lossing's autographs. Says he doesn't mean to sell them singly, but would be willing to sell the letter about which Coffin wrote. Asks for prices brought by various autographed letters at the Burnham Sale. Says he and Dr. Fogg have corresponded for twenty years. Says Fogg supplied one of the drawings engraved in his
    . Mentions some information he recently supplied Fogg and his intention to write Fogg about his own collection. Thanks Coffin for suggestions concerning Fogg and the arrangement of annotations of Lossing's autographs. Expresses a desire to see the letters Coffin purchased at the sale. Speaks of much time spent cataloguing his own autographs. Thanks Coffin forallowing him to keep his Poore ? catalogue. Mentions: George Washington; Nathanael Greene; William Heath; John Stark. ]
  - Benson John Lossing to Helen R. M. Lossing, 1889 March 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Expresses sorrow at her illness; pleasure that she is better. Tells her not to worry about portraits. Tells her he has received three copies of "our book" (probably
    Hours with the Living Men and Women of the Revolution
    ) from Funk and Wagnalls. Says she shouldn't feel that writing him is a necessity.]
- Miscellaneous
  - Copyright agreement between Benson John Lossing and Mason Brothers(publishers) of New York City regarding publication of The Life and Times of Philip Schuyler, 1860 December 18; Printed DS, 3 p.
    [ Mason Brothers is the firm name for Lowell Marson, Jr. and Daniel Gregory Mason. The document was witnessed by M. Aynes. ]
  - Agreement among Benson John Lossing, Francis Baker and George Edward Perine concerning a projected history of New York City to be edited and arranged for the press by Benson John Lossing, 1880 November 3; ADS, 2 p.
    [It was witnessed by Helen R. M. Lossing and Y. L. Perine. In [1844] Perine published
    History of New York City
    by Benson John Lossing; illustrations were engraved on steel by Perine.]
  - "Memorandum" by Benson John Lossing concerning loan from Ulysses Cole of Poughkeepsie, 1881 July 18; ANS, 2 p.
    [Relates the history of the loan, which Cole forgave orally on July 17, 1881, saying he would destroy the note. A short memorandum dated May 1, 1886, says that Cole died without cancelling the note and that Benson John Lossing has paid in full. Mentions: Helen, Fanny, Panic of 1873.]